<!DOCTYPE html><html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xml:lang="en"><head><title>DHArchive</title><meta http-equiv="content-type" content="text/html; charset=utf-8" /><link rel="stylesheet" type="text/css" href="/s/dharchive.css"></link><link rel="shortcut icon" type="image/x-icon" href="favicon.ico" /></head><body><header><a href="/"><img src="/i/logo.png" id="logo" /><h1><acronym>dharchive</acronym>.org</h1></a></header><section><a href="/?c=DH2014"><img src="/data/figures/DH2014/banner.jpg" class="banner"/></a><div id="read"><aside><a class="btn" href="javascript:window.print();"><img src="/i/print.png"/> Print</a><a class="btn" href="/data/xml/DH2014/Poster-525.xml"><img src="/i/download.png"/> XML</a></aside><?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<article xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <header xmlns="">
    <h1>CatCor: Correspondence of Catherine the Great</h1>
    <ul id="details">
      <li><label>Category:</label>Poster</li>
      <li><label>Session:</label>1</li>
      <li><label>Date:</label>2014-07-10<label>Time:</label>14:00:00</li>
      <li><label>Room:</label>Amphipôle Common Area</li>
    </ul>
    <ul id="authors">
      <li>
        <a href="mailto:james.cummings@it.ox.ac.uk"><span class="author-surname">Cummings</span>,
									<span class="author-forename">James</span></a>
        <a href="http://www.google.com/#q=Cummings, James">
          <img src="/i/search.png"/>
        </a>
        <span class="author-affiliation">University of Oxford</span>
      </li>
      <li>
        <a href="mailto:kelsey.rubin-detlev@mod-langs.ox.ac.uk"><span class="author-surname">Rubin-Detlev</span>,
									<span class="author-forename">Kelsey</span></a>
        <a href="http://www.google.com/#q=Rubin-Detlev, Kelsey">
          <img src="/i/search.png"/>
        </a>
        <span class="author-affiliation">University of Oxford</span>
      </li>
      <li>
        <a href="mailto:andrew.kahn@seh.ox.ac.uk"><span class="author-surname">Kahn</span>,
									<span class="author-forename">Andrew</span></a>
        <a href="http://www.google.com/#q=Kahn, Andrew">
          <img src="/i/search.png"/>
        </a>
        <span class="author-affiliation">University of Oxford</span>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </header>
  <p xmlns=""/>
  <p xmlns=""/>
  <p xmlns=""/>
  <h2 xmlns="">CatCor: Correspondence of Catherine the Great</h2>
  <h2 xmlns="">Introduction</h2>
  <p xmlns="">The
CatCor pilot project has produced a searchable online text collection
of the letters of Catherine the Great. This poster examines the
technical background to the project and specifically how the document
analysis and subsequent creation of a TEI P5 customization that
tightly controlled the more general TEI P5 Guidelines produced a
number of significant benefits for the project. These mainly relate
both to the ease of checking of the letters and also the subsequent
development of a website extracting data from this text collection.
This digital humanities project is used as a case study to
demonstrate how, with only very minimal funding, a research project
may be empowered to produce resources that are of clear and immediate
benefit to socio-cultural historians and literary scholars interested
in these materials.  </p>
  <h2 xmlns="">About Catherine the Great's letters</h2>
  <p xmlns="">Catherine
the Great used her correspondence, the primary knowledge-transfer
medium of the Age of Enlightenment, to shape her nation's and her own
role in the political, cultural, and social arenas of Europe. The
collection includes epistolary exchanges with such major figures as
Voltaire, Frederick the Great, Friedrich Melchior Grimm, and
Catherine’s charismatic lover Grigory Potemkin.  Catherine ruled
Russia for 34 years in the second half of the 18th century (from
1762-1796) and her correspondence was the essential medium through
which she governed her court and empire, and established her own and
her nation’s formidable presence in the political life of Europe
and in the intellectual life of the European Enlightenment. Catherine
saw herself as the model Enlightenment monarch, ruling over a nation
that had fully opened itself to European influence and entered the
European consciousness barely 50 years earlier. The primary aim of
her reign was to demonstrate, through both policy initiatives and
public relations efforts, that Russia was a European state.  
</p>
  <h2 xmlns="">The digital collection</h2>
  <p xmlns="">Creating
a digital collection of this unique set of letters allows scholars to
discover unexpected links between letters that have previously been
difficult, if not almost impossible, to juxtapose.  The use of
digital humanities methodologies has meant this project has been able
not only to bring together these disparate and difficult to access
texts, but also enabled new ways of searching, browsing, and
comparing them. While the pilot project only uses 100 letters these
were written by Catherine during two key periods in her
transformative reign, 1774 and 1790-91. Later funding bids will aim
to expand the collection and the project's scope to encompass a
complete collection of Catherine's few thousand extant letters and
also include those sent to her.</p>
  <p xmlns="">The
text of the letters used for the pilot project are encoded in TEI P5
XML and translations to English are provided to facilitate use by a
wider range of researchers.  This markup also allows the letters to
be classified according to a controlled vocabulary of
project-specific themes which are then exposed to users as facets in
the web interface. The project supplements the letters with a new
apparatus of editorial notes and metadata concerning every single
person, place, event, and work mentioned in the correspondence. The
ease of extraction and aggregation of these named entity instances is
one example of the benefits of using a well-known open international
standard and having undertaken the necessary document analysis to
significantly constrain this schema. Once extracted the instances
along with accompanying metadata are able to be displayed, browsed,
and filtered with common technologies such as jQuery DataTables. 
Similarly the use of schematron constraints in the TEI ODD
Customization, and the development of straightforward mechanisms for
simplifying proofing of common aspects of textual collections is
documented in this poster.</p>
  <h2 xmlns="">Conclusion</h2>
  <p xmlns="">The
digital humanities aspects of this project are used as a case study
into the re-usability of the general purpose tools developed for
processing, displaying, and checking basic named entities as well as
other common features of such letters. All of the relevant digital
technologies, including the TEI P5 XML files of the letters, metadata
files, TEI ODD Customization, and XSLT2 functions used for creation
and proofing of the underlying data files are available from a public
github repository under an open license. It is hoped that this will
encourage re-use and empowerment for other digital humanists wishing
to make similar text collections available.  The open source
development work on this project demonstrates the kinds of
sophisticated results, immediately beneficial to the scholars working
on these materials, that can be achieved with limited resources. 
</p>
</article>
</div></section><footer><hr/></footer></body></html>