<!DOCTYPE html><html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xml:lang="en"><head><title>DHArchive</title><meta http-equiv="content-type" content="text/html; charset=utf-8" /><link rel="stylesheet" type="text/css" href="/s/dharchive.css"></link><link rel="shortcut icon" type="image/x-icon" href="favicon.ico" /></head><body><header><a href="/"><img src="/i/logo.png" id="logo" /><h1><acronym>dharchive</acronym>.org</h1></a></header><section><a href="/?c=DH2014"><img src="/data/figures/DH2014/banner.jpg" class="banner"/></a><div id="read"><aside><a class="btn" href="javascript:window.print();"><img src="/i/print.png"/> Print</a><a class="btn" href="/data/xml/DH2014/Poster-350.xml"><img src="/i/download.png"/> XML</a></aside><?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<article xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <header xmlns="">
    <h1>The Text portal: An online resource providing medieval literature for students and their teachers</h1>
    <ul id="details">
      <li><label>Category:</label>Poster</li>
      <li><label>Session:</label>1</li>
      <li><label>Date:</label>2014-07-10<label>Time:</label>14:00:00</li>
      <li><label>Room:</label>Amphipôle Common Area</li>
    </ul>
    <ul id="authors">
      <li>
        <a href="mailto:gerlinde.schneider@uni-graz.at"><span class="author-surname">Schneider</span>,
									<span class="author-forename">Gerlinde</span></a>
        <a href="http://www.google.com/#q=Schneider, Gerlinde">
          <img src="/i/search.png"/>
        </a>
        <span class="author-affiliation">Centre for Information Modelling - Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities, University of Graz</span>
      </li>
      <li>
        <a href="mailto:ylva.schwinghammer@uni-graz.at"><span class="author-surname">Schwinghammer</span>,
									<span class="author-forename">Ylva</span></a>
        <a href="http://www.google.com/#q=Schwinghammer, Ylva">
          <img src="/i/search.png"/>
        </a>
        <span class="author-affiliation">Department of German Studies, University of Graz</span>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </header>
  <p xmlns=""/>
  <p xmlns=""/>
  <p xmlns="">Teaching
material on medieval German literature adequate to present-day educational
standards is insufficiently available. Additionally, the subject tends to be
marginalized in current curricula for teacher training. Consequently, schoolteachers
often lack the impetus and time to prepare and arrange medieval texts for their
students.  </p>
  <p xmlns="">The objective of the publicly funded "Sparkling Science" project
“Arbeitskoffer zu den Steirischen Literaturpfaden des Mittelalters” (Toolbox
for the Styrian literature paths of the
Middle Ages) is to develop an openly accessible, virtual didactic environment
(the “Text portal”) which enables teachers to address the topic of medieval
literature in class and familiarize their students with older German texts. For
that purpose a corpus comprising regional medieval literature is made available
on the Text portal by providing the transcription, translation and facsimiles
of the respective texts. Furthermore, glossarial information and additional
teaching material adapted to the requirements of students on secondary
educational level are featured. </p>
  <p xmlns="">This poster introduces the online resource outlined above which is
developed at the University of Graz in a collaboration between the Department
of German Studies and the Centre for Information Modelling. The main focus is
set on the following two aspects which are fundamental for the realization,
progress and sustainability of the project: </p>
  <h2 xmlns="">
    <strong>1. The inclusion of
prospective users  </strong>
  </h2>
  <p xmlns="">The project primarily targets two disparate groups: Teachers in secondary
education on the one hand and their students on the other hand. In order to
provide an efficient and effective resource, the requirements of both user
groups were considered the guiding principles for the development of the portal
and its underlying data, from the very beginning. </p>
  <p xmlns="">The initiators of the project are scholars of German Studies involved in
the education of both teachers and younger students. In addition to their
individual views on the issue, the requirements to this resource were
elaborated in the context of university courses for teacher training in concert
with actual teachers and teacher trainees. </p>
  <p xmlns="">To investigate the demands of the younger students, a multilayered
empirical analysis was conducted amongst several hundred pupils to survey the
acceptance and comprehension of Middle High German and Early New High German
texts. The outcome of this survey directly influenced later decisions
concerning the selection and edition of the texts provided. </p>
  <p xmlns="">Taking account of the diversity of the prospective user groups, an
intuitive, user-friendly and dependable interface will be realized. With this
goal in mind, the development of the portal is subject to continuous evaluation
within the project team. Further evaluations and test runs in a real-life
environment with students and teachers are scheduled as the project
progresses.</p>
  <h2 xmlns="">
    <strong>2. The involvement of Digital
Humanities competence </strong>
  </h2>
  <p xmlns="">The literary texts provided on the text portal are chosen with regards to their
supraregional importance or their interest within the medieval literary canon,
with the majority not yet being available in a standardized digital format. Enrichment
and annotation methods common in Digital Humanities and the usage of trusted digital
infrastructures serve to produce digital resources in this particular project
which are later reusable in other contexts and sustainably preserved. </p>
  <p xmlns="">All textual sources used within the project are encoded conforming to the
guidelines of TEI P5, annotated and documented in a way that makes an adaption
to further editorial works or other projects as unproblematic as possible. The
TEI representations as well as the pictorial representations and the metadata
of the original sources are openly available via the FEDORA based asset
management system GAMS.</p>
  <h2 xmlns="">References</h2>
  <p xmlns=""><strong><strong>Hockey, S.</strong></strong> (2012).
          Digital Humanities in the Age of the Internet: Reaching Out to Other
          Communities. In Deegan, M. and McCarty, W. (eds), <em>Collaborative Research in
            the Digital Humanities.</em> Farnham: Ashgate, pp. 81-92.</p>
  <p xmlns=""><strong><strong>Kümper, H.</strong></strong>(2011). Mittelalter und Mittelalterunterricht im neumedialen Zeitalter. In
          Kümper, H. (ed.), <em>eLearning &amp; Mediävistik.</em> Frankfurt am Main: Peter
          Lang, pp. 7-65.</p>
  <p xmlns=""><strong><strong>Schmidt, S.</strong></strong> (2004). Neue Medien und alte Themen: Internet &amp; Co als
          Vermittlungshilfen in der Schule, im Museum und an der Universität. In van Eickels,
          K., Weichselbaumer, R. and Bennewitz, I. (eds), <em>Mediaevistik und Neue
            Medien.</em> Ostfildern: Thorbecke, pp. 243-259.</p>
  <p xmlns=""><strong><strong>TEI Consortium</strong></strong> (2013). <em>TEI
          P5: Guidelines for Electronic Text Encoding and Interchange, Version 2.5.0.</em>
          Virginia: Text Encoding Initiative Consortium Charlottesville.</p>
  <p xmlns=""><strong><strong>Warwick, C.</strong></strong> (2012).
          Studying Users in Digital Humanities. In Warwick, C., Terras, M. and Nyhan, J.
          (eds), <em>Digital Humanities in Practice.</em> London: Facet Publishing, pp. 1-22.</p>
</article>
</div></section><footer><hr/></footer></body></html>