<!DOCTYPE html><html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xml:lang="en"><head><title>DHArchive</title><meta http-equiv="content-type" content="text/html; charset=utf-8" /><link rel="stylesheet" type="text/css" href="/s/dharchive.css"></link><link rel="shortcut icon" type="image/x-icon" href="favicon.ico" /></head><body><header><a href="/"><img src="/i/logo.png" id="logo" /><h1><acronym>dharchive</acronym>.org</h1></a></header><section><a href="/?c=DH2014"><img src="/data/figures/DH2014/banner.jpg" class="banner"/></a><div id="read"><aside><a class="btn" href="javascript:window.print();"><img src="/i/print.png"/> Print</a><a class="btn" href="/data/xml/DH2014/Poster-762.xml"><img src="/i/download.png"/> XML</a></aside><?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<article xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <header xmlns="">
    <h1>The Digitization of Hmong Sacred Texts</h1>
    <ul id="details">
      <li><label>Category:</label>Poster</li>
      <li><label>Session:</label>2</li>
      <li><label>Date:</label>2014-07-10<label>Time:</label>16:00:00</li>
      <li><label>Room:</label>Amphipôle Common Area</li>
    </ul>
    <ul id="authors">
      <li>
        <a href="mailto:"><span class="author-surname">Ogden</span>,
									<span class="author-forename">Mitchell Paul</span></a>
        <a href="http://www.google.com/#q=Ogden, Mitchell Paul">
          <img src="/i/search.png"/>
        </a>
        <span class="author-affiliation">University of Wisconsin–Stout, US</span>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </header>
  <p xmlns=""/>
  <p xmlns="">A remote
religious community, called Ee Nbee Mee Noo (Ib Npis Mis Nus), in northern Thailand has recently shared their
extensive collection of hand-written religious manuscripts with researchers
following extensive collaboration and community work. Interested in making
these foundational sacred texts more accessible across the global Hmong
diaspora, the community leaders sought the cooperation of scholars to digitize
the texts in preparation for eventual publication. Rich in historical and
religious content, these nine 200-page volumes are written in the community’s
own sacred and obscure Puaj Txwm alphabet
of the Hmong language.</p>
  <p xmlns="">The
scope of our project includes the development of a set of digital tools that
will perform OCR (built on the Tesseract engine), error-check based on
phonological rules of the Hmong language, and encode the text (according to TEI
guidelines) to make the text searchable and indexable for future distribution
as electronic texts. In addition, the project will create a transliteration
tool that will enable Hmong texts to be transliterated across the dozen or more
orthographies used throughout the diaspora, thus facilitating the exchange and
investigation of Hmong language texts across diasporic histories and
geographies.</p>
  <p xmlns="">This
poster will feature the project’s tools and process, emphasizing the solutions
to obstacles including a hand-written manuscript and the complicated politics
of ethnic minority religious movements in Thailand. The poster will provide
context for these sacred texts and their obscure alphabet, overview the
digitization process, and provide examples of the work and the innovative
solutions developed by our research team.</p>
</article>
</div></section><footer><hr/></footer></body></html>