<!DOCTYPE html><html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xml:lang="en"><head><title>DHArchive</title><meta http-equiv="content-type" content="text/html; charset=utf-8" /><link rel="stylesheet" type="text/css" href="/s/dharchive.css"></link><link rel="shortcut icon" type="image/x-icon" href="favicon.ico" /></head><body><header><a href="/"><img src="/i/logo.png" id="logo" /><h1><acronym>dharchive</acronym>.org</h1></a></header><section><a href="/?c=DH2014"><img src="/data/figures/DH2014/banner.jpg" class="banner"/></a><div id="read"><aside><a class="btn" href="javascript:window.print();"><img src="/i/print.png"/> Print</a><a class="btn" href="/data/xml/DH2014/Workshops-436.xml"><img src="/i/download.png"/> XML</a></aside><?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<article xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <header xmlns="">
    <h1>Introduction to Starting and Sustaining DH Centers</h1>
    <ul id="details">
      <li><label>Category:</label>Workshops</li>
      <li><label>Session:</label></li>
      <li><label>Date:</label>2014-07-08<label>Time:</label>09:00:00</li>
      <li><label>Room:</label>2A - SwissTech</li>
    </ul>
    <ul id="authors">
      <li>
        <a href="mailto:siemensl@uvic.ca"><span class="author-surname">Siemens</span>,
									<span class="author-forename">Lynne</span></a>
        <a href="http://www.google.com/#q=Siemens, Lynne">
          <img src="/i/search.png"/>
        </a>
        <span class="author-affiliation">University of Victoria</span>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </header>
  <p xmlns=""/>
  <h2 xmlns="">1. Introduction to Starting and Sustaining DH Centers</h2>
  <h2 xmlns="">Description</h2>
  <p xmlns="">Digital Humanities is growing in scale from a series projects undertaken by a couple of individuals to institutionally-based organizations, with larger budgets and mandates, beyond other factors. How can a group of interested researchers, academic staff, librarians and other invested stakeholders work together to create such a centre? This half-day workshop will address this question by exploring issues related to scaling operations from the individual to a centre, determining the appropriate organizational model, developing the plan which situates the DH centre in the academic institution’s and other stakeholders’ mandates, communicating to administration to gain support and resources, structuring memorandums of understanding between partners, and other issues.  It builds on centerNet’s iniatitives to support center startups with information and tools, which include the DHCenterStartUp listserv and resources page (<a href="digitalhumanities.org/centernet/resources-for-starting-and-sustaining-dh-centers">http://digitalhumanities.org/centernet/resources-for-starting-and-sustaining-dh-centers/</a>).</p>
  <h2 xmlns="">Workshop leader</h2>
  <p xmlns="">Dr. Lynne Siemens, Assistant Professor, School of Public Administration, University of Victoria and centerNet’s Coordinator for Center Startups with centerNet.</p>
  <p xmlns="">Dr. Siemens is an Assistant Professor at the University of Victoria.  Her interests include academic entrepreneurship, collaboration and teamwork with a focus on understanding methods and processes to facilitate collaborative research across distances, disciplines and organizational boundaries.  Beyond publishing in these areas, she has taught workshops in Project Management at University of Victoria’s Digital Humanities Summer Institute and University of Leipzig's European Summer School for Culture and Technology and serves as a management advisor for Implementing New Knowledge Environments (INKE), a Major Collaborative Research Initiative project.  Dr. Siemens is also centerNet’s Coordinator for Center Startups and coordinates the DHCenterStartUp listserv and the resources for starting DH centers webpage.</p>
  <p xmlns="">CenterNet is an international network of digital humanities centers.  Part of its mandate is to support the development of centers at a variety of institutions by sharing information, resources and expertise.</p>
  <h2 xmlns="">Contact Information</h2>
  <p xmlns="">Lynne Siemens</p>
  <p xmlns="">School of Public Administration</p>
  <p xmlns="">University of Victoria</p>
  <p xmlns="">Victoria, British Columbia Canada</p>
  <p xmlns="">V8W 2Y2</p>
  <p xmlns="">(250) 721-8069</p>
  <p xmlns="">siemensl@uvic.ca</p>
  <h2 xmlns="">Target audience and expected number of participants</h2>
  <p xmlns="">The target audience is individuals interested in starting a Digital Humanities center at their institution. Expected number of participants is 15-20. (These numbers are in line with previous offerings of similar workshops/talks.)</p>
  <h2 xmlns="">Intended length and format of workshop</h2>
  <p xmlns="">The workshop will be a half-day with a combination of lecture and discussion. No special technical requirements or equipment is needed.</p>
</article>
</div></section><footer><hr/></footer></body></html>