<!DOCTYPE html><html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xml:lang="en"><head><title>DHArchive</title><meta http-equiv="content-type" content="text/html; charset=utf-8" /><link rel="stylesheet" type="text/css" href="/s/dharchive.css"></link><link rel="shortcut icon" type="image/x-icon" href="favicon.ico" /></head><body><header><a href="/"><img src="/i/logo.png" id="logo" /><h1><acronym>dharchive</acronym>.org</h1></a></header><section><a href="/?c=DH2014"><img src="/data/figures/DH2014/banner.jpg" class="banner"/></a><div id="read"><aside><a class="btn" href="javascript:window.print();"><img src="/i/print.png"/> Print</a><a class="btn" href="/data/xml/DH2014/Poster-419.xml"><img src="/i/download.png"/> XML</a></aside><?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<article xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <header xmlns="">
    <h1>Exploring Qualitative Data for Secondary Analysis: Challenges, Methods, and Technologies</h1>
    <ul id="details">
      <li><label>Category:</label>Poster</li>
      <li><label>Session:</label>1</li>
      <li><label>Date:</label>2014-07-10<label>Time:</label>14:00:00</li>
      <li><label>Room:</label>Amphipôle Common Area</li>
    </ul>
    <ul id="authors">
      <li>
        <a href="mailto:bischoff@l3s.de"><span class="author-surname">Bischoff</span>,
									<span class="author-forename">Kerstin</span></a>
        <a href="http://www.google.com/#q=Bischoff, Kerstin">
          <img src="/i/search.png"/>
        </a>
        <span class="author-affiliation">L3S Research Center</span>
      </li>
      <li>
        <a href="mailto:niederee@l3s.de"><span class="author-surname">Niederée</span>,
									<span class="author-forename">Claudia</span></a>
        <a href="http://www.google.com/#q=Niederée, Claudia">
          <img src="/i/search.png"/>
        </a>
        <span class="author-affiliation">L3S Research Center</span>
      </li>
      <li>
        <a href="mailto:ntran@l3s.de"><span class="author-surname">Tran</span>,
									<span class="author-forename">Nam Khanh</span></a>
        <a href="http://www.google.com/#q=Tran, Nam Khanh">
          <img src="/i/search.png"/>
        </a>
        <span class="author-affiliation">L3S Research Center</span>
      </li>
      <li>
        <a href="mailto:zerr@l3s.de"><span class="author-surname">Zerr</span>,
									<span class="author-forename">Sergej</span></a>
        <a href="http://www.google.com/#q=Zerr, Sergej">
          <img src="/i/search.png"/>
        </a>
        <span class="author-affiliation">L3S Research Center</span>
      </li>
      <li>
        <a href="mailto:peter.birke@sofi.uni-goettingen.de"><span class="author-surname">Birke</span>,
									<span class="author-forename">Peter</span></a>
        <a href="http://www.google.com/#q=Birke, Peter">
          <img src="/i/search.png"/>
        </a>
        <span class="author-affiliation">Soziologisches Forschungsinstitut Göttingen</span>
      </li>
      <li>
        <a href="mailto:"><span class="author-surname">Brückweh</span>,
									<span class="author-forename">Kerstin</span></a>
        <a href="http://www.google.com/#q=Brückweh, Kerstin">
          <img src="/i/search.png"/>
        </a>
        <span class="author-affiliation">Universität Trier, Neuere und Neueste Geschichte</span>
      </li>
      <li>
        <a href="mailto:wiede@uni-trier.de"><span class="author-surname">Wiede</span>,
									<span class="author-forename">Wiebke</span></a>
        <a href="http://www.google.com/#q=Wiede, Wiebke">
          <img src="/i/search.png"/>
        </a>
        <span class="author-affiliation">Universität Trier, Neuere und Neueste Geschichte</span>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </header>
  <p xmlns=""/>
  <p xmlns=""/>
  <p xmlns=""/>
  <p xmlns=""/>
  <p xmlns=""/>
  <p xmlns=""/>
  <p xmlns=""/>
  <h2 xmlns="">Introduction</h2>
  <p xmlns="">A remarkable
body of data has been collected in the social sciences by interviewing people
or observing peoples’ interaction in a variety of situations – qualitative data
sources very valuable for contemporary research. Notable projects promoting the
re-use of qualitative data are ESDS Qualidata <cite href="#n1">1</cite> (now UK Data Service) or
Bequali <cite href="#n2">2</cite>. Here, we discuss important challenges in re-using qualitative
data for secondary analysis and present first ideas on how to overcome them.
This includes exploiting state-of-the-art IT-methods from the fields of
Information Retrieval and Data Mining – adapting and integrating them for the
digital humanities – as well as methodological considerations based on
interdisciplinary work, in our case between computer scientists, historians, and
social scientists in the project “Gute Arbeit” <cite href="#n3">3</cite>.</p>
  <h2 xmlns="">Challenges
in secondary analysis of qualitative data</h2>
  <p xmlns="">We focus on challenges on three main levels: a)
making qualitative data <strong><strong>accessible</strong></strong> for
secondary analysis, b) making relevant material <strong><strong>findable</strong></strong>, and c) making it <strong><strong>understandable</strong></strong>,
i.e., ensuring adequate interpretation. </p>
  <h2 xmlns="">
    <strong>Accessibility</strong>
  </h2>
  <p xmlns="">Efforts towards secondary analysis of qualitative data often have to
struggle with researchers’ reluctance to make their data – their asset –
(digitally) available. One crucial issue is warranting anonymity. The problem
is exacerbated with qualitative data since answers are rather uncontrolled and
unstructured, making it possible to combine information from various places in
an interview, e.g., potentially giving information on an employee's (rather
unique) background. There is an inherent conflict: While the data owners may
tend to prefer protecting their clients, other researchers will argue for
having complete information on interview content and context.</p>
  <h2 xmlns="">
    <strong>Findability</strong>
  </h2>
  <p xmlns="">The ability to select the right primary material is an important
precondition for re-analysis. For this, tools for exploring and searching
relevant studies, cases/samples, and documents are needed that allow defining
various criteria and notions of interesting or “similar” data. Furthermore,
when reading and analysing the selected (long) interviews we envision enhanced
analysis support, e.g. for re-using and sharing codes and annotations or for
within document navigation to snippets of interest.</p>
  <h2 xmlns="">
    <strong>Interpretability</strong>
  </h2>
  <p xmlns="">Understanding context is crucial to correctly
interpret utterances of interviewees. Lack of context knowledge (“Not having
been there”) is usually stated as one of the major
concerns regarding the feasibility of secondary analysis <cite href="#n4">4</cite>. Furthermore, some qualitative approaches
consider interactions between researchers and interviewees as essential for
interpretation <strong/><cite href="#n5">5</cite>. While for some
studies e.g., ethnological field studies, (contextual) data may not be sharable
at all, for semi-structured interviews the process of data gathering can be
made more transparent <cite href="#n6">6</cite>. Moreover,
when working with data from earlier time periods questions of (the
comparability of) socio-cultural macro-context are raised <cite href="#n7">7</cite>.</p>
  <h2 xmlns="">Technologies
for digitally enhanced secondary analysis of qualitative data</h2>
  <p xmlns="">In current practice, qualitative researchers mainly rely on qualitative
data analysis tools like ATLAS.ti or MaxQDA or on (quantitative)
dictionary-based content analysis tools, e.g., General Inquirer or Diction.
Here, we discuss how secondary analysis of qualitative data can benefit
from more sophisticated techniques from text mining and natural language
processing – especially when systematically combining them to reveal novel
usages.  </p>
  <h2 xmlns="">Named Entity Recognition</h2>
  <p xmlns="">Automatically identifying persons,
organizations, and locations, i.e., so called named entity recognition (NER),
is a standard task in natural language processing with tools publicly available,
e.g. Stanford Named Entity Recognizer <cite href="#n8">8</cite>.
In secondary analysis, NER can be used for improving search (e.g., faceted
search) and contextualization. While non-disclosure agreements and adequate access rights will be the
cornerstone of an anonymization strategy, NER can also assist in the anonymization task
by finding persons or organizations talked about or by highlighting location
names, which possibly provide additional hints to who was interviewed. Identified
named entities can be systematically substituted by pseudonyms – storing the
mapping safely on a remote place. </p>
  <h2 xmlns="">Sentiment Analysis</h2>
  <p xmlns="">Opinion
mining (sentiment analysis) techniques could support the secondary researcher
in finding opinionated material, e.g., passages with positive or negative points
of view on a particular subject. For example, our project “Gute Arbeit”
is interested in how peoples' concepts of “good" work evolved over the
last decades.  Besides, such techniques may support judging the
sensitivity of material, e.g. insults. Direct application of – often
vocabulary-based – state-of-the-art sentiment analysis tools (e.g. <cite href="#n9">9</cite>) to
qualitative data is usually not feasible. There are peculiarities regarding the
detection of subjective expressions and opinion targets, context dependency,
indirect opinions, and ordering or omittance effects. For example, in
face-to-face interviews subtle sentiment expressions are common. We are
researching how to ‘train’ machine-learning approaches to better cope with
qualitative data.</p>
  <h2 xmlns="">Topic Modeling</h2>
  <p xmlns="">Topic modeling with its prominent
representative Latent Dirichlet allocation (LDA) <cite href="#n10">10</cite> is a statistical technique for identifying the topical structure
of large textual corpora. Application to limited size qualitative corpora may
require gathering additional training data (<cite href="#n11">11</cite>, <cite href="#n12">12</cite>).Topic
modeling techniques can highlight themes - possibly going beyond themes asked
for - discussed in (long) qualitative documents. Concept Maps or co-occurrence
matrixes are related ideas. For a quick overview, interview contents can be
visualized by means of representative topics. For example, topics extracted
from a collection of studies show commonalities while comparing topics of
individual studies sheds light on specifics. Similarly, Janasik et al. <cite href="#n13">13</cite> argue that such text mining procedures can aid
both data-driven, inductive research by finding emergent concepts as well as
theory-driven, deductive research by checking the adequacy and applicability of
defined schemes.</p>
  <h2 xmlns="">Context Enrichment</h2>
  <p xmlns="">There are different kinds and levels of context
of the interview, e.g., conversational, situational, regarding the research
project, or institutional/cultural <cite href="#n14">14</cite>.
While most of these context variables need to be documented by the primary
researcher, IT tools can substantially aid capturing the socio-cultural
(macro-)context present at the time of data collection. Using external
knowledge bases, e.g. Wikipedia or news corpora, primary data can be
automatically annotated and linked with background information (e.g. <cite href="#n15">15</cite>, <cite href="#n16">16</cite>, <cite href="#n17">17</cite>). Changes in socio-cultural context may also be better traceable by
topic or word clusters with their evolution tracked over time <cite href="#n18">18</cite>.</p>
  <h2 xmlns="">Intelligent Search and Visualization</h2>
  <p xmlns="">For fast access to an archive of unknown qualitative studies, intelligent
search procedures and advanced visualizations for supporting exploration are
crucial: Term clouds, Topics maps, and timelines, e.g. for word (cluster)
evolutions. Facetted search is a standard in many web applications allowing to
browse data or to filter query results based on facets. For a qualitative data
archive such facets can be classical metadata like project or study, year, or
author, but also advanced information extracted automatically, like entities or
topics talked about. All of these may help the secondary researcher to better
define his notion of interesting or “similar” material.</p>
  <p xmlns="">While quite many projects make use of one of the aforementioned techniques,
novel usage scenarios result from systematically chaining or plugging in the
various components. Of course, to aid digital humanities researchers IT tools
need to adhere to best practices in interface and interaction design (usability
principles like learnability, robustness). More importantly, scepticism
regarding the utility and validity of employing IT techniques in humanities
research as well as potential misperceptions of ‘hostile takeover’ attempts
have to be addressed. </p>
  <h2 xmlns="">First experiences </h2>
  <p xmlns="">The technologies discussed hold a lot of promise for supporting secondary
analysis, but it is important to carefully fit the way they are offered with
the work practices and expectations for secondary analysis. Due to the close
collaboration across disciplines as well as the work on concrete secondary
analysis tasks, our project “Gute Arbeit” provides a good hands-on opportunity
for such user-driven technology adaption. We conducted two group discussions
where an early prototype realizing topic modelling via Mallet <cite href="#n19">19</cite> was shown as a
stimulus to each three humanities researchers. Despite some limitations in
perceived quality, in sum our researchers stated an added value regarding data
access and exploration – though considerably less for those very familiar with
the data. In general, the need for iterative interaction, flexibility, and personalization
were put forward by both groups. For example, instead of aiming at automatic
topic labelling users want to maintain their own topic labels and as well define
relationships between topics or group topics into clusters. Thresholds for
probability-based techniques like topic modeling should be adjustable to allow
trading off completeness versus specificity. By enabling ranking based on
relative (cumulative) topic coverage one can easily focus on the most relevant
subset of documents that cover most of the topic in the corpus. Contrasting
different subsets of documents matching criteria like study, profession, or time period regarding prevalent topics was mentioned as an
interesting further development. Especially for the historian, the time
dimension was important. Language and topic evolution could be visualized.</p>
  <p xmlns="">Our experiments showed the need to select and adapt text mining tools
carefully - here tailoring the technology to the needs of secondary analysis.
The lessons learned through our interdisciplinary, collaborative, agile
approach to tool development highlight the methodological strengths of the
rapid prototyping process: researchers get to know and trust the techniques
better as these early hands-on sessions demonstrate potentials as well as
necessary refinements. While it is hard to know your requirements for novel
digital research tools before seeing them in action, iteratively providing (imperfect)
evolutionary prototypes seems a useful methodology for establishing a common
ground for the Digital Humanities.</p>
  <h2 xmlns="">References</h2>
  <p xmlns="">1. 
            <a href="http://www.esds.ac.uk/qualidata/about/introduction.asp">www.esds.ac.uk/qualidata/about/introduction.asp</a></p>
  <p xmlns="">2. 
            <a href="http://www.bequali.fr/">www.bequali.fr/</a></p>
  <p xmlns="">3. 
            <a href="http://www.sofi-goettingen.de/index.php?id=1086">www.sofi-goettingen.de/index.php?id=1086</a></p>
  <p xmlns="">4. 
            <strong>Corti, L., Witzel, A., and Bishop, L.</strong> (2005). <em>On the Potentials and Problems of Secondary Analysis</em>. An Introduction to the FQS Special Issue on Secondary Analysis of Qualitative Data. Forum Qualitative Sozialforschung / Forum: Qualitative Social Research, 6(1).
          </p>
  <p xmlns="">5. 
            <strong>Gillies, V. and Edwards, R.</strong> (2005). <em>Secondary Analysis in Exploring Family and Social Change: Addressing the Issue of Context</em>. Forum Qualitative Sozialforschung / Forum: Qualitative Social Research, 6(1).
          </p>
  <p xmlns="">6. 
            <strong>Irwin, S.</strong> (2013). <em>Qualitative secondary data analysis: Ethics, epistomology and context</em>. Progress in Development Studies, 13(4):295-306.</p>
  <p xmlns="">7. 
            <strong>Gillies, V. and Edwards, R.</strong> (2005). <em>Secondary Analysis in Exploring Family and Social Change: Addressing the Issue of Context</em>. Forum Qualitative Sozialforschung / Forum: Qualitative Social Research, 6(1).</p>
  <p xmlns="">8. 
            <strong>Finkel, J. R., Grenager, T., and Manning, C.</strong> (2005). <em>Incorporating Non-local Information into Information Extraction Systems by Gibbs Sampling</em>, Proceedings of the 43nd Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics, ACL, University of Michigan, USA, June 2005.</p>
  <p xmlns="">9. 
            <strong>Pang, B. and Lee, L.</strong> (2008). <em>Opinion Mining and Sentiment Analysis. Foundations and Trends in Information Retrieval</em>, 2(1-2):1-135.</p>
  <p xmlns="">10. 
            <strong>Blei, D. M., Ng, A. Y., and Jordan, M. I. </strong>(2003). <em>Latent dirichlet allocation. The Journal of Machine Learning Research</em>, 3:993-1022.</p>
  <p xmlns="">11. 
            <strong>Zhu, X., He, X., Munteanu, C., and Penn, G.</strong> (2008). <em>Using latent Dirichlet allocation to incorporate domain knowledge for topic transition detection</em>. Proceedings of the 9th Annual Conference of the International Speech Communication Association, INTERSPEECH, Brisbane, Australia, September 2008:2443-2445.</p>
  <p xmlns="">12. 
            <strong>Tran, N. K., Zerr, S., Bischoff, K., Niederée, C., and Krestel, R. </strong>(2013). <em>Topic Cropping: Leveraging Latent Topics for the Analysis of Small Corpora. Research and Advanced Technology for Digital Libraries - Proceedings of the International Conference on Theory and Practice of Digital Libraries</em>, TPDL, Valetta, Malta, September 2013, Springer LNCS, pp. 297-308.
          </p>
  <p xmlns="">13. 
            <strong>Janasik, N., Honkela, T. and Bruun, H.</strong> (2009).<em> Text mining in qualitative research: Application of an unsupervised learning method</em>. Organizational Research Methods, 12(3):436-460.
          </p>
  <p xmlns="">14. 
            <strong>Bishop, L.</strong> (2006). <em>A Proposal for Archiving Context for Secondary Analysis</em>. Methodological Innovations Online, 1(2):10-20.
          </p>
  <p xmlns="">15. 
            <strong>Mihalcea, R. and Csomai, A. </strong>(2007). <em>Wikify!: linking documents to encyclopedic knowledge</em>. Proceedings of the sixteenth ACM conference on Conference on information and knowledge management, CIKM, Lisbon, Portugal, 2007, ACM, pp. 233–242.
          </p>
  <p xmlns="">16. 
            <strong>Milne, D. and Witten, I. H.</strong> (2008).<em> Learning to link with Wikipedia</em>. Proceedings of the 17th ACM conference on Information and knowledge management, CIKM, Napa Valley, CA, USA, October 2008, ACM, pp. 509–518.
          </p>
  <p xmlns="">17. 
            <strong>He, J., de Rijke, M., Sevenster, M., van Ommering, R., and Qian, Y.</strong> (2011).<em> Generating links to background knowledge: a case study using narrative radiology reports</em>. Proceedings of the 20th ACM Conference on Information and Knowledge Management, CIKM, Glasgow, Scotland, UK, 2011, ACM, pp. 1867–1876.
          </p>
  <p xmlns="">18. 
            <strong>Wang, X. and McCallum, A.</strong> (2006). <em>Topics over time: a non-markov continuous-time model of topical trends</em>. Proceedings of the 12th ACM SIGKDD international conference on Knowledge discovery and data mining, KDD, Philadelphia, PA, USA, August 2006, ACM, pp. 424-433.
          </p>
  <p xmlns="">19. 
            <strong>McCallum, A. K.</strong>  (2002). <em>MALLET: A Machine Learning for Language Toolkit</em>, <a href="http://mallet.cs.umass.edu.">mallet.cs.umass.edu.</a></p>
</article>
</div></section><footer><hr/></footer></body></html>