<!DOCTYPE html><html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xml:lang="en"><head><title>DHArchive</title><meta http-equiv="content-type" content="text/html; charset=utf-8" /><link rel="stylesheet" type="text/css" href="/s/dharchive.css"></link><link rel="shortcut icon" type="image/x-icon" href="favicon.ico" /></head><body><header><a href="/"><img src="/i/logo.png" id="logo" /><h1><acronym>dharchive</acronym>.org</h1></a></header><section><a href="/?c=DH2014"><img src="/data/figures/DH2014/banner.jpg" class="banner"/></a><div id="read"><aside><a class="btn" href="javascript:window.print();"><img src="/i/print.png"/> Print</a><a class="btn" href="/data/xml/DH2014/Poster-885.xml"><img src="/i/download.png"/> XML</a></aside><?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<article xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <header xmlns="">
    <h1>TextGrid: Creating, archiving, publishing and exploring digital editions and other humanistic research data via a Virtual Research Environment</h1>
    <ul id="details">
      <li><label>Category:</label>Poster</li>
      <li><label>Session:</label>1</li>
      <li><label>Date:</label>2014-07-10<label>Time:</label>14:00:00</li>
      <li><label>Room:</label>Amphipôle Common Area</li>
    </ul>
    <ul id="authors">
      <li>
        <a href="mailto:sibylle.soering@sub.uni-goettingen.de"><span class="author-surname">Söring</span>,
									<span class="author-forename">Sibylle</span></a>
        <a href="http://www.google.com/#q=Söring, Sibylle">
          <img src="/i/search.png"/>
        </a>
        <span class="author-affiliation">Georg-August-Universität Göttingen, Niedersächsische Staats- und Universitätsbibliothek, Germany </span>
      </li>
      <li>
        <a href="mailto:"><span class="author-surname">Veentjer</span>,
									<span class="author-forename">Ubbo</span></a>
        <a href="http://www.google.com/#q=Veentjer, Ubbo">
          <img src="/i/search.png"/>
        </a>
        <span class="author-affiliation">Georg-August-Universität Göttingen, Niedersächsische Staats- und Universitätsbibliothek, Germany </span>
      </li>
      <li>
        <a href="mailto:"><span class="author-surname">Funk</span>,
									<span class="author-forename">Stefan</span></a>
        <a href="http://www.google.com/#q=Funk, Stefan">
          <img src="/i/search.png"/>
        </a>
        <span class="author-affiliation">Georg-August-Universität Göttingen, Niedersächsische Staats- und Universitätsbibliothek, Germany </span>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </header>
  <p xmlns=""/>
  <p xmlns=""/>
  <p xmlns=""/>
  <p xmlns="">Today, scholarly
digital editions represent one of the core application areas of the Digital
Humanities. Virtual Research Environments (VREs) enable and support the
creation, publication, and long-term archiving of such data. Answering an increasing demand for digital and
collective research features in the humanities, the joint project TextGrid, funded by the German Federal Ministry of Education
and Research has, since its start in 2006 and in continuous exchange with the research
community, developed a VRE that aims at mapping the entire research process. </p>
  <p xmlns="">

Whereas the <strong><strong>TextGrid Laboratory</strong></strong> (TextGridLab)  contains a versatile open source software for
editing and generating digital sources collaboratively in a protected virtual
environment, and allowing for a differentiated user rights management, the <strong><strong>TextGrid Repository</strong></strong> (TextGridRep) offers
an open, XML/TEI-based long-term research archive, in which both the text and
image data generated with the TextGridLab, as well as external digital objects,
can be published, browsed, explored, analysed, cited, and archived. </p>
  <p xmlns="">A crucial factor of a VRE’s success and impact is the use
of both technological and semantic standards. The TextGrid architecture
supports, amongst common metadata standards, the markup language XML together
with the well-established markup data format TEI. They reflect
international standards for the sustainable, searchable and reusable mark-up of
humanistic sources, especially of digital editions. A differentiated user rights management facilitates
collaborative work on a shared project in a non-public environment. Tools, data,
and methods can be used mutually, regardless of the operative system, software
equipment, or location. </p>
  <p xmlns="">In addition to the tools
and services available in the TextGridLab, the TextGridRep provides the user
with the possibility to save, publish, and search a variety of digital
resources such as XML/TEI encoded texts, images and databases, therefore
supporting the creation of Linked Open Data. Thus, both core components of the
VRE, the TextGridLab and the TextGridRep, are aligned for an optimal
interaction, interlinkeage, and workflow between and with one another.</p>
  <p xmlns="">Beyond the creation
of resources, TextGrid ensures the persistent availability of and access to
research data as well as optimal interconnectivity, supporting international
standards. Collaborative research is facilitated by e.g. the annotation of
images; further annotation features are currently evaluated. </p>
  <p xmlns="">Thus, TextGrid facilitates
the creation of digital editions, from the provision and creation of primary
data in XML to published and citable research data; data that can also be made
available in an external online portal, or be exported into a print-ready
document (PDF).</p>
  <p xmlns="">As of today, TextGrid has
approx. 1.500 registered users and approx. 40 research projects from a broad
spectrum of humanistic disciplines ranging from philology, cultural studies,
medieval studies, jewish and ecclesiastical history to linguistic and
musicological studies. Amongst them are single scholars and medium-scale
research groups such as "Theodor Fontane's notebooks", as well as large,
long-term projects like “Johann Friedrich Blumenbach – online” or “IDIOM –
Interdisciplinary Dictionary of Classic Mayan”. </p>
  <p xmlns="">The poster will display how a complete scholarly workflow can be mapped
via a VRE like TextGrid – from collecting and generating primary data through
enriching it with metadata and XML/TEI, and finally publishing it in a portal
and/or a repository, following sustainable standards and thus allowing for
citation, long-term accessibility, further interlinking and scholarly re-use. In
this scope, the poster will not only focus on text-based research data, but
will also explore technologies allowing for a web based annotation, viewing and
publishing of image formats such as Digilib.</p>
  <div xmlns="" class="figure">
    <img src="/data/figures/DH2014/textgridusagescenarioen.jpg"/>
    <figcaption/>
  </div>
  <div xmlns="" class="figure">
    <img src="/data/figures/DH2014/textgridrepenv3.jpg"/>
    <figcaption/>
  </div>
  <h2 xmlns="">References</h2>
  <p xmlns="">http://www.textgrid.de/en/</p>
  <p xmlns="">https://www.textgrid.de/en/registrationdownload/download-and-installation/</p>
  <p xmlns="">http://www.textgridrep.de/</p>
  <p xmlns=""> http://www.tei-c.org/index.xml</p>
  <p xmlns="">http://www.uni-goettingen.de/en/303691.html</p>
  <p xmlns=""> http://www.blumenbach-online.de/index.php?id=2&amp;L=1</p>
  <p xmlns="">http://www.iae.uni-bonn.de/forschung/forschungsprojekte/laufende-projekte/idiom-dictionary-of-classic-mayan/idiom-english-project-description</p>
  <p xmlns="">http://digilib.berlios.de/</p>
</article>
</div></section><footer><hr/></footer></body></html>