<!DOCTYPE html><html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xml:lang="en"><head><title>DHArchive</title><meta http-equiv="content-type" content="text/html; charset=utf-8" /><link rel="stylesheet" type="text/css" href="/s/dharchive.css"></link><link rel="shortcut icon" type="image/x-icon" href="favicon.ico" /></head><body><header><a href="/"><img src="/i/logo.png" id="logo" /><h1><acronym>dharchive</acronym>.org</h1></a></header><section><a href="/?c=DH2014"><img src="/data/figures/DH2014/banner.jpg" class="banner"/></a><div id="read"><aside><a class="btn" href="javascript:window.print();"><img src="/i/print.png"/> Print</a><a class="btn" href="/data/xml/DH2014/Poster-375.xml"><img src="/i/download.png"/> XML</a></aside><?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<article xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <header xmlns="">
    <h1>An easy tool for creating digital scholarly editions</h1>
    <ul id="details">
      <li><label>Category:</label>Poster</li>
      <li><label>Session:</label>1</li>
      <li><label>Date:</label>2014-07-10<label>Time:</label>14:00:00</li>
      <li><label>Room:</label>Amphipôle Common Area</li>
    </ul>
    <ul id="authors">
      <li>
        <a href="mailto:dumont@bbaw.de"><span class="author-surname">Dumont</span>,
									<span class="author-forename">Stefan</span></a>
        <a href="http://www.google.com/#q=Dumont, Stefan">
          <img src="/i/search.png"/>
        </a>
        <span class="author-affiliation">Berlin-Brandenburg Academy of Sciences and Humanities</span>
      </li>
      <li>
        <a href="mailto:fechner@bbaw.de"><span class="author-surname">Fechner</span>,
									<span class="author-forename">Martin</span></a>
        <a href="http://www.google.com/#q=Fechner, Martin">
          <img src="/i/search.png"/>
        </a>
        <span class="author-affiliation">Berlin-Brandenburg Academy of Sciences and Humanities</span>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </header>
  <p xmlns=""/>
  <p xmlns=""/>
  <p xmlns="">The
Berlin Brandenburg Academy of Sciences and Humanities (BBAW) is home
to multiple long term research projects which encompass various
fields of study. The research group TELOTA (The Electronic Life of
the Academy) supports the digital humanities aspects of these
projects, including developing software solutions for the daily work
of their researchers. 
</p>
  <p xmlns="">Experience
shows that although using
TEI-XML encoding<cite href="#n1">1</cite>
for the digital transcription and annotation of manuscripts can
improve research in edition projects,  the
readiness to implement it greatly relies on
the user-friendliness of the entry interface. From the perspective of
a researcher, working directly in XML  simply
doesn't compare to the ease of programs
like MS Word. A new software solution must therefore at least offer
the same amount of editorial comfort as such programs. Ideally, it
would also encompass the complete life-cycle of an edition: from the
first phases of transcription to the final publication.</p>
  <p xmlns="">TELOTA
developed such a software solution “ediarum”<cite href="#n2">2</cite>,
which can be
adapted to the needs of  different research
projects. The solution consists of various
software components that allow the researchers to construct and edit
transcriptions of manuscripts and
manuscript descriptions into XML following
the TEI guidelines. Through editing and
tagging manuscripts, a large quantity of digital data can be
generated and is prepared
for further research and presentation. The
solution includes the possibility to create
apparatuses of different kinds, as well as to create without much
additional effort both a print and web publication.</p>
  <p xmlns="">The
central software component of the new digital work environment
“ediarum” is
Oxygen XML Author<cite href="#n3">3</cite>. The researcher does not edit the XML code
directly, but instead works in a user-friendly Author mode, which is
designed through Cascading Stylesheets (CSS). The researcher is able
to choose more than one perspective within the Author view, and thus
can select per mouse click the appropriate perspective for the
current task. Additionally, a toolbar is provided with which the
researcher can enter markup with the push of a button. In this way
text phenomena such as deletions or additions, or editorial
commentary, are easily inserted. Person and place names can also be
recorded with their appropriate TEI markup, and in addition they can
be simultaneously linked to the corresponding index. This is done
through selecting the name from a convenient drop down list. The
entire manuscript text can thus be quickly and simply marked up with
TEI conform XML. All documents are stored
in the open source database "existdb".<cite href="#n4">4</cite></p>
  <p xmlns="">Besides
creating a digital work environment for
“ediarum” in Oxygen XML Author, a
website can also
be built based on
eXistdb, XQuery,
and XSLT. Through the website the researchers can easily page through
or search the current data inventory.</p>
  <p xmlns="">Through
the intergration
of ConTeXt<cite href="#n5">5</cite> into “ediarum”
a further publication type, a print
edition,  can
automatically be generated
as a PDF from the TEI XML document. The layout and format imitates
previously printed volumes of critical editions.
Each TEI element must be
given a specific formatting command through a configuration file. In
this way the different apparatuses appear as footnotes that refer to
the main text with the help of line numbers and lemmata. The print
edition can also provide the suitable index for each transcription
and solves any occurring cross references between manuscripts.</p>
  <p xmlns="">This
work environment has been in use since 2012
by the staff of different research projects
for their daily work. When asked their
opinion, the researchers were in agreement
that the new work environment greatly eased their editorial work and
saved them significant time. The possibility to directly check the
results of their work in a web presentation or as a printed edition
was seen as an additional positive aspect.</p>
  <p xmlns="">Presently
“ediarum” is
used by the edition of letters, lectures
and diaries of the German
theologian Friedrich Schleiermacher<cite href="#n6">6</cite>; the description of medieval
manuscripts of Aristoteles or the regesta of emperor Friedrich III.
 For each project the TEI XML schemata and
main functions were customized to the different manuscript types and
needs. In the future, “ediarum”
will be implemented for further projects of the academy or other
institutions, e.g. the edition of Jeremias
Gotthelfs prints and manuscripts at the University of Bern (Suisse).</p>
  <h2 xmlns="">Screenshots</h2>
  <div xmlns="" class="figure">
    <img src="/data/figures/DH2014/DH2014_310_schleiermacher_workflow_EN.jpg"/>
    <figcaption>
      <p>Fig. 1: Workflow of ediarum</p>
    </figcaption>
  </div>
  <div xmlns="" class="figure">
    <img src="/data/figures/DH2014/DH2014_310_toolbar_schleiermacher.jpg"/>
    <figcaption>
      <p>Fig. 2: Customized TEI toolbar in Oxygen XML Author for the digital edition of Friedrich Schleiermachers letters, lectures and diaries</p>
    </figcaption>
  </div>
  <div xmlns="" class="figure">
    <img src="/data/figures/DH2014/DH2014_310_screenshot_oxygen_komplett2.jpg"/>
    <figcaption>
      <p>Fig. 3: Transcription of a letter in Oxygen XML Author</p>
    </figcaption>
  </div>
  <h2 xmlns="">References</h2>
  <p xmlns="">1. <strong>Burnard, Lou; Bauman, Syd</strong> (Hg.): <em>TEI P5: Guidelines for Electronic Text Encoding and Interchange</em>. Charlottesville, Virginia, USA 2007. URL: <a href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/Guidelines.pdf">www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/Guidelines.pdf</a></p>
  <p xmlns="">2. <a href="http://www.bbaw.de/en/telota/software/ediarum">www.bbaw.de/en/telota/software/ediarum</a></p>
  <p xmlns="">3. User Manual Oxygen XML Author 14. URL: <a href="http://www.oxygenxml.com/doc/ug-editor/">www.oxygenxml.com/doc/ug-editor/</a></p>
  <p xmlns="">4. eXist Main Documentation. URL: <a href="http://www.exist-db.org/exist/documentation.xml">www.exist-db.org/exist/documentation.xml</a></p>
  <p xmlns="">5. ConTeXt Dokumentation. URL: <a href="http://wiki.contextgarden.net/Main_Page">wiki.contextgarden.net/Main_Page</a></p>
  <p xmlns="">6. <strong>Dumont, Stefan; Fechner, Martin</strong>: <em>Digitale Arbeitsumgebung für das Editionsvorhaben »Schleiermacher in Berlin 1808—1834</em> In: di	giversity — Webmagazin für Informationstechnologie in den Geisteswissenschaften. URL: <a href="http://digiversity.net/2012/digitale-arbeitsumgebung-fur-das-editionsvorhaben-schleiermacher-in-berlin-1808-1834">digiversity.net/2012/digitale-arbeitsumgebung-fur-das-editionsvorhaben-schleiermacher-in-berlin-1808-1834</a></p>
</article>
</div></section><footer><hr/></footer></body></html>