<!DOCTYPE html><html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xml:lang="en"><head><title>DHArchive</title><meta http-equiv="content-type" content="text/html; charset=utf-8" /><link rel="stylesheet" type="text/css" href="/s/dharchive.css"></link><link rel="shortcut icon" type="image/x-icon" href="favicon.ico" /></head><body><header><a href="/"><img src="/i/logo.png" id="logo" /><h1><acronym>dharchive</acronym>.org</h1></a></header><section><a href="/?c=DH2014"><img src="/data/figures/DH2014/banner.jpg" class="banner"/></a><div id="read"><aside><a class="btn" href="javascript:window.print();"><img src="/i/print.png"/> Print</a><a class="btn" href="/data/xml/DH2014/Poster-389.xml"><img src="/i/download.png"/> XML</a></aside><?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<article xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <header xmlns="">
    <h1>L’Innommable / The Unnamable: The Second Module of the Samuel Beckett Digital Manuscript Project’s Hybrid Genetic Edition.</h1>
    <ul id="details">
      <li><label>Category:</label>Poster</li>
      <li><label>Session:</label>1</li>
      <li><label>Date:</label>2014-07-10<label>Time:</label>14:00:00</li>
      <li><label>Room:</label>Amphipôle Common Area</li>
    </ul>
    <ul id="authors">
      <li>
        <a href="mailto:wout.dillen@gmail.com"><span class="author-surname">Dillen</span>,
									<span class="author-forename">Wout</span></a>
        <a href="http://www.google.com/#q=Dillen, Wout">
          <img src="/i/search.png"/>
        </a>
        <span class="author-affiliation">University of Antwerp</span>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </header>
  <p xmlns=""/>
  <p xmlns="">This poster will
offer an interactive demonstration of the second module of the <em>Samuel Beckett Digital Manuscript Project</em>
(BDMP) – an international collaboration between the Centre for Manuscript
Genetics at the University of Antwerp, the Beckett International Foundation at
the University of Reading, and the Harry Ransom Humanities Research Center at
the University of Austin, Texas, with the kind permission of the Estate of
Samuel Beckett. As its name implies, the BDMP aims to reunite and make
publicly accessible all manuscripts of Samuel Beckett’s works, the physical
documents of which are located in different holding libraries around the world.
This goal will be realized in the form of a hybrid genetic edition that
combines a digital archive of the manuscripts organized in twenty-six research
modules (one published each year) with a series of twenty-six accompanying
volumes analysing the geneses of the texts contained in the corresponding
modules. Each of the modules comprises digital facsimiles and transcriptions of
all extant manuscripts pertaining to an individual text – or to a collection of
shorter texts. The digital archive can be accessed online at <a href="http://www.beckettarchive.org">www.beckettarchive.org</a>, where you can currently find
the project’s first module, which combines the manuscripts of the late short
prose text <em>Stirrings Still / Soubresauts</em>with
those of Beckett’s last poem <em>Comment dire
/ what is the word<cite href="#n1">1</cite></em>. The project’s second module, which will present the
bilingual genetic dossier of Beckett’s novel <em>L’Innommable / The Unnamable</em> edited by Dirk Van Hulle, Shane
Weller and Vincent Neyt, will be made available online towards the end of 2013<cite href="#n2">2</cite>.</p>
  <p xmlns="">As
a hybrid genetic edition, the BDMP combines digital scholarly editing with
genetic criticism – a form of literary criticism that studies the dynamics of
the writing process. As such, the edition does not aim to support a new reading
text of Beckett’s works, but rather to highlight the creative process that
brought those works about. Traces of this process can be found in the extant
manuscripts, more specifically in their many deletions, additions, paralipomena,
doodles, etc. According to Pierre-Marc de Biasi, the objective of genetic
criticism is twofold (42)<cite href="#n3">3</cite>: first (1) to locate, collate, and transcribe all of
the work’s extant versions in order to make them analysable, and then (2) to
reconstruct the logic of the work’s genesis (also called the ‘avant texte’) from a chosen perspective.
Therefore, rather than focussing solely on an <em>analysis</em> of the works’ geneses – which can be found in the
interpretative, printed component of our edition – we also want to make these
geneses <em>analysable</em>, by offering fully
transcribed (in TEI-compliant XML) and searchable facsimiles in the edition’s
digital component. Hence, the BDMP complies with Patrick Sahle’s recent
definition of scholarly hybrid editions, stipulating that such editions should
not only be published in different media, but that their different components
should complement one another, and that each component should take the
possibilities and limitations of its medium into account (64)<cite href="#n4">4</cite>.</p>
  <p xmlns="">Because the modern manuscripts we exhibit are
still under copyright and therefore do not yet belong to the public domain, the
BDMP still requires its users (either individuals or institutions) to pay a
subscription fee to gain access to its materials. Therefore, this poster will be a
great opportunity for potential users to receive a personal, hands-on
introduction to the project. The poster’s main focus will be on the project’s
newest module, and on the differences between both modules. Because the genesis
of every work is different, even within the oeuvre of a single author, we try to determine what the specific needs of the texts in each
subsequent module are, and to re-evaluate the tools and functionalities the
module will provide to satisfy those needs accordingly. For the BDMP’s second
module, for example, this resulted in changes to the Synoptic Sentence View
(which allows the user to grab any sentence in our corpus, and generate a
chronological list of its different versions), to the image-text linking tool,
etc. Furthermore, this poster will also demonstrate the BDMP’s improved
integration of CollateX<cite href="#n5">5</cite> – the interoperable collation tool that is part of the
Interedition project<cite href="#n6">6</cite>. </p>
  <h2 xmlns="">References</h2>
  <p xmlns="">1. <strong>Beckett, Samuel</strong> (2011). <em>Stirrings Still / Soubresauts and Comment Dire / what is the word: an electronic genetic edition</em> (Series ‘The Beckett Digital Manuscript Project’ module 1), edited by Dirk Van Hulle and Vincent Neyt. Brussels: University Press Antwerp (ASP/UPA). <a href="http://www.beckettarchive.org">www.beckettarchive.org</a> (accessed 30 October 2013).
          </p>
  <p xmlns="">2. <strong>Beckett, Samuel</strong> (2011). <em>Stirrings Still / Soubresauts and Comment Dire / what is the word: an electronic genetic edition</em> (Series ‘The Beckett Digital Manuscript Project’ module 1), edited by Dirk Van Hulle and Vincent Neyt. Brussels: University Press Antwerp (ASP/UPA). <a href="http://www.beckettarchive.org">www.beckettarchive.org</a> (accessed 30 October 2013).
          </p>
  <p xmlns="">3. <strong>de Biasi, Pierre-Marc</strong> (2004) <em>Toward a Science of Literature: Manuscript Analysis and the Genesis of the Work.</em> Genetic Criticism. Texts and Avant-textes. Philadelphia: University of Pennsylvania Press: 36-68.
          </p>
  <p xmlns="">4. <strong>Sahle, Patrick</strong> (2013) <em>Digitale Editionsformen, Zum Umgang mit der Überlieferung unter den Bedingungen des Medienwandels</em>. Teil 2: Befunde, Theorie und Methodik. Nordstedt: Books on Demand.
          </p>
  <p xmlns="">5. <strong>CollateX</strong> (2013) <em>Home.</em> CollateX. <a href="http://www.collatex.net">www.collatex.net</a> (accessed 30 October 2013).
          </p>
  <p xmlns="">6. <strong>Interedition</strong> (2013) <em>Home.</em> Interedition. <a href="http://www.interedition.eu">www.interedition.eu</a> (accessed 30 October 2013).
          </p>
</article>
</div></section><footer><hr/></footer></body></html>